<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://tingdiren.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://tingdiren.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-08-21T07:54:34+00:00</updated><id>https://tingdiren.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">TingdiRen</title><subtitle>Tingdi Ren&apos;s academic website. A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">From Fairness to Functions: Schur-Concavity and the Principle of Transfers</title><link href="https://tingdiren.github.io/blog/2025/Schur/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Fairness to Functions: Schur-Concavity and the Principle of Transfers"/><published>2025-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tingdiren.github.io/blog/2025/Schur</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tingdiren.github.io/blog/2025/Schur/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="1-motivation">1. Motivation</h3> <p>How can we rigorously compare the fairness of different income distributions? Consider two societies, A and B, each with the same total income, say $100, distributed among two individuals. In society A, the distribution is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">(90, 10)</code>. In society B, it is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">(50, 50)</code>. Intuitively, most would agree that society B has a more equitable distribution of income.</p> <p>Now, consider a third society, C, with a distribution of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">(80, 20)</code>. We might feel that C is more equitable than A, but less so than B. What is the underlying principle guiding this intuition? In 1920, economists Arthur Pigou and Hugh Dalton independently articulated it: a distribution of income is more equal if it can be achieved from another by a transfer of income from a richer person to a poorer person, provided the transfer is not so large as to reverse their relative ranks. This is now known as the <strong>Pigou-Dalton principle of transfers</strong>.</p> <p>For instance, we can move from society A’s <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">(90, 10)</code> to society C’s <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">(80, 20)</code> by taking $10 from the richer individual and giving it to the poorer one. This “Robin Hood” operation seems to unambiguously increase social welfare, or at least reduce inequality.</p> <p>This raises a crucial question for the theorist: How can we formalize this principle? What mathematical property must a social welfare function <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">W(x_1, x_2, ..., x_n)</code> possess to guarantee that it always prefers distributions that are more equal in the Pigou-Dalton sense? We need a precise mathematical language to capture the idea of “more unequal than” and a corresponding class of functions that respect this ordering.</p> <h3 id="2-introducing-schur-concavity">2. Introducing Schur-Concavity</h3> <p>To answer the economic question, we must first introduce the concepts of <em>majorization</em> and <em>Schur-concavity</em>.</p> <h4 id="21-formal-definition">2.1 Formal Definition</h4> <p>Let $x = (x_1, \dots, x_n)$ and $y = (y_1, \dots, y_n)$ be two vectors in $\mathbb{R}^n$. Let $x_{(1)} \ge x_{(2)} \ge \dots \ge x_{(n)}$ denote the components of $x$ sorted in descending order, and similarly for $y$.</p> <p><strong>Definition: Majorization</strong> We say that the vector $x$ <strong>majorizes</strong> the vector $y$, denoted $x \succ y$, if the following two conditions hold:</p> <ol> <li>$\sum_{i=1}^k x_{(i)} \ge \sum_{i=1}^k y_{(i)}$ for all $k = 1, \dots, n-1$.</li> <li>$\sum_{i=1}^n x_{(i)} = \sum_{i=1}^n y_{(i)}$.</li> </ol> <p>Intuitively, majorization captures a sense in which the components of vector $x$ are “more spread out” or “less equal” than the components of vector $y$, while maintaining the same total sum.</p> <p>With this, we can define a class of functions that are ordered by majorization.</p> <p><strong>Definition: Schur-Concavity and Schur-Convexity</strong> A function $f: D \to \mathbb{R}$, where $D \subseteq \mathbb{R}^n$ is a symmetric set (i.e., if $x \in D$, then any permutation of $x$ is also in $D$), is said to be:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Schur-concave</strong> if for any $x, y \in D$, $x \succ y \implies f(x) \le f(y)$.</li> <li><strong>Schur-convex</strong> if for any $x, y \in D$, $x \succ y \implies f(x) \ge f(y)$.</li> </ul> <p>A Schur-concave function gives a higher value to vectors whose components are more “even,” while a Schur-convex function favors vectors whose components are more “spread out.”</p> <h4 id="22-key-properties-and-theorems">2.2 Key Properties and Theorems</h4> <p>A crucial result connects Schur-concavity to more familiar concepts from microeconomic theory.</p> <p><strong>Theorem (Schur-Ostrowski):</strong> Let $f: \mathbb{R}^n \to \mathbb{R}$ be a symmetric and continuously differentiable function. Then $f$ is Schur-concave if and only if for all $x \in \mathbb{R}^n$ and all $i \neq j$: \(\left( \frac{\partial f}{\partial x_i} - \frac{\partial f}{\partial x_j} \right) (x_i - x_j) \le 0\) This condition has a powerful interpretation: if an individual $i$ has more than individual $j$ ($x_i &gt; x_j$), then the marginal contribution of an additional unit to individual $i$ must be less than or equal to its marginal contribution to individual $j$ ($\frac{\partial f}{\partial x_i} \le \frac{\partial f}{\partial x_j}$). This is a formal statement of diminishing marginal returns.</p> <p>A more direct and widely used result is:</p> <p><strong>Theorem:</strong> Any function that is symmetric and quasi-concave is Schur-concave.</p> <h4 id="23-an-illustrative-non-economic-example">2.3 An Illustrative (Non-Economic) Example</h4> <p>Let’s consider vectors in $\mathbb{R}^3$. Let $x = (10, 2, 0)$, $y = (6, 6, 0)$, and $z = (4, 4, 4)$. Note that the sum of components for each vector is 12.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Comparing $x$ and $y$</strong>: <ul> <li>Sorted vectors: $x_{(1)}=10, x_{(2)}=2, x_{(3)}=0$; $y_{(1)}=6, y_{(2)}=6, y_{(3)}=0$.</li> <li>$k=1$: $10 \ge 6$. (Holds)</li> <li>$k=2$: $10+2 \ge 6+6 \implies 12 \ge 12$. (Holds)</li> <li>$k=3$: $10+2+0 = 6+6+0 \implies 12 = 12$. (Holds)</li> <li>Therefore, $x \succ y$. The vector $(10, 2, 0)$ is more “spread out” than $(6, 6, 0)$.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Comparing $y$ and $z$</strong>: <ul> <li>Sorted vectors: $y_{(1)}=6, y_{(2)}=6, y_{(3)}=0$; $z_{(1)}=4, z_{(2)}=4, z_{(3)}=4$.</li> <li>$k=1$: $6 \ge 4$. (Holds)</li> <li>$k=2$: $6+6 \ge 4+4 \implies 12 \ge 8$. (Holds)</li> <li>$k=3$: $6+6+0 = 4+4+4 \implies 12 = 12$. (Holds)</li> <li>Therefore, $y \succ z$.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>Now, consider the function $f(x_1, x_2, x_3) = -(x_1^2 + x_2^2 + x_3^2)$. This function is symmetric and concave, and therefore Schur-concave. Let’s check:</p> <ul> <li>$f(x) = f(10, 2, 0) = -(100 + 4 + 0) = -104$.</li> <li>$f(y) = f(6, 6, 0) = -(36 + 36 + 0) = -72$.</li> <li>$f(z) = f(4, 4, 4) = -(16 + 16 + 16) = -48$.</li> </ul> <p>As expected, since $x \succ y \succ z$, we have $f(x) \le f(y) \le f(z)$. The function assigns the highest value to the most “equal” vector, $z$.</p> <h3 id="3-applying-schur-concavity-to-welfare-economics">3. Applying Schur-Concavity to Welfare Economics</h3> <p>We are now equipped to bridge the gap between the economic intuition and the mathematical formalism. The connection is remarkably direct and elegant.</p> <p>A Pigou-Dalton transfer is an operation that takes an income vector $x$ and produces a new vector $y$ by transferring a small amount $\delta &gt; 0$ from a richer individual $i$ to a poorer individual $j$ (where $x_i &gt; x_j$). The new vector $y$ has components $y_i = x_i - \delta$, $y_j = x_j + \delta$, and $y_k = x_k$ for all other $k$. For the transfer to be rank-preserving, we require $x_i - \delta \ge x_j + \delta$.</p> <p>A fundamental result in the theory of majorization is that any such transfer produces a vector that is majorized by the original. That is, if $y$ is obtained from $x$ by a single Pigou-Dalton transfer, then <strong>$x \succ y$</strong>.</p> <p>The economic requirement that a social welfare function $W$ must satisfy the Pigou-Dalton principle is the statement:</p> <blockquote> <p>If $y$ is obtained from $x$ via a Pigou-Dalton transfer, then $W(y) \ge W(x)$.</p> </blockquote> <p>The mathematical definition of a Schur-concave function is:</p> <blockquote> <p>If $x \succ y$, then $W(x) \le W(y)$.</p> </blockquote> <p>Since a Pigou-Dalton transfer implies $x \succ y$, the two statements are equivalent. <strong>A social welfare function satisfies the Pigou-Dalton principle of transfers if and only if it is Schur-concave.</strong></p> <p>This is a powerful result. It tells us that the intuitive ethical preference for equality, as captured by the Pigou-Dalton principle, has a precise and identifiable mathematical counterpart. Any social welfare function we might propose—such as a utilitarian <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">W = \sum u(x_i)</code> or a Rawlsian <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">W = \min\{x_i\}</code>—can be immediately checked for this basic notion of fairness by testing for Schur-concavity. Furthermore, because any symmetric and quasi-concave function is Schur-concave, we know that our standard assumptions on social welfare functions (anonymity/symmetry and a preference for diversification/averages) automatically embed this fundamental principle of inequality aversion.</p> <h3 id="4-concluding-remarks">4. Concluding Remarks</h3> <p>Schur-concavity provides the rigorous foundation for the study of inequality measurement. It transforms an ethical postulate—the Pigou-Dalton principle—into a testable mathematical property, allowing for the systematic analysis and comparison of social welfare functions.</p> <h3 id="5-references">5. References</h3> <ol> <li>Atkinson, A. B. (1970). “On the Measurement of Inequality.” <em>Journal of Economic Theory</em>, 2(3), 244-263.</li> <li>Marshall, A. W., Olkin, I., &amp; Arnold, B. C. (2011). <em>Inequalities: Theory of Majorization and Its Applications</em> (2nd ed.). Springer.</li> <li>Mas-Colell, A., Whinston, M. D., &amp; Green, J. R. (1995). <em>Microeconomic Theory</em>. Oxford University Press. (See the mathematical appendix on convexity and related concepts).</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Mathematical-Economics"/><category term="Schur-concavity"/><category term="Majorization"/><category term="Pigou-dalton-principle"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An introduction to Schur-concavity, bridging the gap between the intuitive Pigou-Dalton principle of transfers and the formal mathematics of inequality measurement in welfare economics.]]></summary></entry></feed>